A Guide to the Papers of Thomas Jefferson and the Randolph Family, 1784-1918
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Thomas Jefferson and the Randolph Family 1784-1918
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9828
The collection consists of 92 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was deposited in the library by Mary Kirk Moyer of Geneva, N.Y., 1972 November 16.
Scope and Content
The majority of the Jefferson items are financial papers, including accounts with James Monroe, although a few convey family news. The remainder of the collection is an assortment of correspondence and miscellaneous papers of the Randolph family. It contains financial papers, printed reminiscences, obituary notices, poetry, and architectural drawings.
Topics include the publication of books by Thomas Jefferson Randolph and Sarah Nicholas Randolph, the settling of Jefferson's estate, refutation of libel against Jefferson by overseer Edmund Bacon in Parton's biography, the Edgehill school run by the Randolph sisters, and the last illnesses and deaths of several family members.
Correspondents include John Barnes, William Bernard, Sue B. Blackburn, Mary Jefferson Bolling, Sidney S. Nicholas Carr, Reuben Clarkson, Joseph Coolidge, Susan Coolidge, John Dunlop, Francis Eppes, Maria Jefferson Eppes, John S. H. Fogg, Paul Leicester Ford, Eleanora Wayles Randolph Harrison, Maria Jefferson Carr Randolph Mason, and Caroline Ramsay Randolph.
Other correspondents include Cary Ruffin Randolph, Cornelia Jefferson Randolph, Jane Hollins Nicholas Randolph, Martha Jefferson Randolph, Meriwether Lewis Randolph, Cary Anne Nicholas Randolph Ruffin, Eliza McDonald Ruffin, Eliza McDonald Ruffin, John Speyer, Jefferson Randolph Taylor, Patty Taylor, Nicholas Philip Trist, and William Fanning Wickham.
Contents List
- Series 1: Papers of Thomas Jefferson
  - Thomas Jefferson Early Drawing of Monticello, [1771-1772], AD, 1 p.; Photostat. For original see Nichols, N-47. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Study for final elevation of the first version. [2347; N-47] #5291.
  - Thomas Jefferson Household Expenses, 1784 February 24-April 1, ANS, 1 p.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:2)
    A list of purchased articles with their price.
  - Invitation to Dinner with Massachusetts Delegation, 1784 February 29, AD, 2 pp. on 1 l; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Inviting the delegation to dinner with a list of household expense account with James Monroe in Thomas Jefferson's hand.
  - Fragment of Personal Record of Household Expenses Account with James Monroe, 1784 March 14-21, AD, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:4)
    A list of purchased items with their prices.
  - Personal Copy of Accounts with James Monroe, 1784 March 14-May 8, AN, 2 pp. on 1 l; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Mary Bolling to Thomas Jefferson, 1787 May 3, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Concerning her desire that her bother, Thomas Jefferson, break a long epistolary silence despite the fact that she "supposed it was [because] the publick had taken [his] attention." Longs for his return and a visit.
  - Martha Jefferson to Thomas Jefferson, 1787 May 26, ALS, 1 p.; Photograph; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Martha Jefferson writes to her father, Thomas Jefferson, expecting him and her sister [Maria] in Paris in July. Describes her activities in Paris including playing the harpsichord, studying history, and drawing landscapes and flowers. Mentions Madam de Taubenheim who sends her compliments to Jefferson, and will keep a bed for his visiting daughter if they visit in July.
  - Mary Bolling to Thomas Jefferson, 1791 April 6, ALS, 1 p.; docketed; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:8)
    Describing her "disappointment" at her brother's, Thomas Jefferson's, absence "at a time that [her family's] distress cannot be described." Mary "hail[s him] grandfather" and hopes he will be able to see "the little stranger," [Ann Cary Randolph], the following Spring. Informs Jefferson that Sister Carr's ill health is worsening.
  - Thomas Jefferson, Philadelphia, to Maria Jefferson, Varina, 1797 March 11, AL, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:9)
    Tells her news of her friends, Miss Geddis and Miss McKain. Worries that Miss Bruni will take offense at his inability to provide her with a carriage ride. Desires her to stay in Varina "because [he] think[s] it better for [her] to go more into society that the neighborhood of Monticello admits." [Folder also includes a photograph of the Peale painting of Jefferson] Original in Thomas Jefferson papers and accessioned as #38-576.
  - Thomas Jefferson to Mr. John Barnes, 1799 September 17, ANS, 1 p.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:10)
    Authorizing payment of $500 to Bethune and Smith of New York for George Jefferson & Co.
  - Thomas Jefferson to Mr. John Barnes, 1801 June 9, ANS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:11)
    Authorizing payment of twenty dollars to two foreign ecclesiastics on account of [service].
  - Thomas Jefferson to John Barnes, 1801 July 20, ANS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:12)
    Requesting the addition of books and articles to a shipment of groceries to Richmond, and for twenty dollars in small bills.
  - Bill from Conrad & Mc Mun to Thomas Jefferson, 1801 October 24, ADS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:13)
    Bill for one pair of looking glasses with signed authorization for payment to Mr. Barnes on 1801 October 26.
  - Bill for J. B. Anderson for Three Frames, 1802 June 6, ANS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:14)
    Bill for three frames for three prints with signed authorization for Mr. [John] Barnes to pay the bill for Thomas Jefferson 1802 October 5.
  - Thomas Jefferson to [John] Barnes, 1802 November 16, ANS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:15)
    John Barnes to give Captain Lewis forty dollars for expenses of journey to be taken for his family.
  - Bill from Sam Carr to William Lyles, 1803 May 20, ANS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:16)
    Bill for eighteen barrels of herrings and freight to Alexandria. Thomas Jefferson signed authorization for payment by Mr. Barnes 1803 June 1.
  - Thomas Jefferson to [John] Barnes, 1803 July 1, ANS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:17)
    Authorizing a payment of five dollars from Edward Frethy for one month's lodging.
  - Thomas Jefferson to John Barnes, 1804 January 15, ANS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:18)
    Authorizing payment of $80.58 to Joseph Daugherty for the expenses of filling the ice house.
  - Thomas Jefferson to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1808 October 27, ALS, 1 p.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:19)
    Thomas Jefferson asks Randolph to send his watch with either Dr. Porter or Dr. Say, who will be coming for the sitting of Congress. He also asks Randolph to have Mr. McAlister, an optician, make a magnifying glass and includes a small sketch of the design. Thomas Jefferson encloses ten dollars for two alabaster lamps.
  - John Speyer to Thomas Jefferson, 1812 November 12, ALS, 1 p. with attached address leaf; Postmarked New York, February 13; With an additional note that it was forwarded to London 1812 December 14; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:20)
    Request for favor on an enclosed letter (missing) sent on recommendation of mutual friend Madame de Stael.
  - Thomas Jefferson's Medical Balance Sheet, 1815 [September], ANS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:21)
    Dr. William Steptoe's medical balance sheet for Thomas Jefferson.
  - Bill of Lading, 1816 May 28, AD, 1 p.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:22)
    Bill of lading to a consignment of wine and macaroni shipped to Thomas Jefferson from Philadelphia.
  - Thomas Jefferson to His Fellow Citizens, [ca. 1824], AL file draft, 1 p.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:23)
    Describing his prior commitment to answering letters, but requesting that in his old age "letters will cease to be expected from him," because of his "decayed energies of body & mind."
  - Thomas Jefferson to Francis Eppes, 1826 March 9, AL draft, 2 pp. on 1 l. with address; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:24)
    Answer to a letter from Eppes inquiring about a bill to sell a portion of Thomas Jefferson's property to settle debts. Also asking advice about law practices written on the address leaf of Eppes' letter.
  - List of Paintings, [182-], ANs, 14 pp.; Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:25)
    Names forty-eight paintings and art works, often with artists and sources. Subjects are chiefly religious, classical, mythological, and historical.[Probably a list of works Thomas Jefferson wanted for Monticello, since most were eventually found in Monticello.]
  - Rough sketch of Monticello, n.d., Original transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:26)
    Rough sketch of outlines of the house terrace and grounds of Monticello by Thomas Jefferson.
  - Printed Jefferson Invitations and Calling Cards, n.d., 4 items. (Box-folder 1:27)
    Three different styles of calling card and one invitation card.
- Series 2: Papers of the Randolph Family
  - Newspaper Clippings about Thomas Jefferson's Life and Career, [ca. 1802]-1907 (Box-folder 1:28)
    Daily Richmond Enquirer, 1852 April 21. Thomas Jefferson. Concerning Jefferson's life and accomplishments.
    The Weekly Chronicle, 1875 October 15. Jefferson. Reprinting a letter of Andrew K. Smith's to the Washington Republican concerning his personal reminiscences of Thomas Jefferson. Concerning Jefferson's final days and funeral arrangements. Provides an anecdote about a controversy over whether citizens of Charlottesville and students would be allowed to attend the funeral, and that a group of fifteen hundred missed the interment. He claims to have seen Edgar Allan Poe at the funeral.
    Unidentified, ante-1802 October. Civil List: Officers of the Federal Government. Contains a list of all the prominent government officers of the United States, including Thomas Jefferson, Aaron Burr, and James Madison.
    Cincinnati Commercial, 1877 May 15. The Resolutions of '98. Who was their author? Printing four letters concerning the author of the Kentucky Resolution of 1798. One by Colonel Donan to Colonel Breckinridge, 1877 May 6 desiring to publish Breckenridge's letter to him about a misattribution often made by the historians of the time. One by Colonel Breckenridge to Colonel Donan, 1877 May 3 concerning the misattribution of the recipient of a letter by Thomas Jefferson to a son of George Nicholas, and claims that the real recipient was a son of John Breckenridge's. One from Colonel Breckenridge to Colonel Donan, 1877 May 11 concerning John Breckenridge's position on State rights in relation to Jefferson's, and the Breckenridge family legacy. One from Thomas Jefferson to J. Cabell Breckenridge, 1821 December 21 concerning Jefferson's reminiscences of the origin of the Kentucky Resolution, and the original letter whose recipient had been misattributed according to Colonel Breckenridge.
    The Washington Herald, 1907 April 13. Stories of Thomas Jefferson. Written on the one hundred and sixty fourth anniversary of Jefferson's birthday. Containing an extended editorial on the modesty of the inscription on Jefferson's grave stone, the accomplishments left out of such a thumbnail sketch, and an anecdote about Jefferson's behavior on the day of the dedication of The University of Virginia.
    The Last Days of Jefferson, Jeffersonian Print, [1873]. Thomas Jefferson Randolph's critique of James Parton and Edmund Bacon's account of the Last Days of Jefferson. Repudiates Edmund Bacon's account as the "fiction of an old man." Provides a point by point refutation of many of Bacon's claims, and finishes with an extended defense of his father's, Col. Thomas Mann Randolph's, character from the "unmitigated falsehoods" of Edmund Bacon. Original transferred to Broadsides 1873 .R36. copy 2.
    Unidentified. "Th. Jefferson. An Interesting Autograph Letter from the Father of Democracy." Reprints a July 14, 1801 letter of Thomas Jefferson's concerning a payment of six hundred dollars to Craven Peyton.
    Unidentified. Thomas Jefferson's Bible. Concerning a resolution introduced in Congress to commission the publication of Thomas Jefferson's Life and Morals of Jesus of Nazareth and provides a description of its composition.
  - B[ernard C.] Peyton to T[homas] Jefferson [Randolph], [18]17 December 22, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:29)
    Concerning the price of rent, the prospects of a brokered purchase of a woman who "is worth $300 [to] 400 cash." He also apologizes for a mistake and lists the prices of crops.
  - Bern[ard] C. Peyton to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1823 November 24, ALS, 1 p. with address on verso; docketed; Postmarked Richmond, VA, November 24. (Box-folder 1:30)
    Concerning debts that are coming due, and lists the prices of various crops.
  - Bernard [C.] Peyton to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1824 January 1, ALS, 1 p. with attached address leaf; docketed; Postmarked Richmond, VA, January 1. (Box-folder 1:31)
    Concerning payment to the literary fund, and his having requested Mr. Christian to make a statement of the interest due to the University. Also lists the price of crops.
  - B[ernard C.] Peyton to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1824 February 16, ALS, 1 p. with address on verso; docketed; Postmarked Richmond, VA, February 1[6]. (Box-folder 1:32)
    Concerning debts and the price of crops.
  - B[ernard C.] Peyton to [Thomas] Jefferson [Randolph], 1824 April 29, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:33)
    Concerning debts.
  - B[ernard C.] Peyton to Th[omas] Jefferson Randolph, 1824 June 26, ALS, 1 p. with address on verso; docketed; Postmarked Richmond, VA, June 26. (Box-folder 1:34)
    Concerning interest on a loan from William and Mary College, and Mr. Christian's upcoming meeting with the Visitors of the College.
  - Bernard [C.] Peyton to Th[omas] Jeff[erson] Randolph, 1824 August 21, ALS, 1 p. with attached address leaf; docketed. (Box-folder 1:35)
    Relates that the Port Master, Dr. [Foushee], has "kicked the bucket," and that Peyton is an applicant to fill the now vacant position. Asks for Randolph to curry favor in and around Tufton, and claims that the President will do likewise.
  - Bern[ard] C. Peyton to Thomas J[efferson] Randolph, 1824 July 8, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with attached address leaf; docketed; Postmarked Richmond, VA, July 8. (Box-folder 1:36)
    Tells him to allay his fears about interest due to William and Mary; will try to deposit #1400 at the Virginia Bank, and, only if that fails, in the Farmer's Bank "where nothing is certain." Lists debts he has paid on Randolph's behalf, and crop prices.
  - Thomas J[efferson] Randolph to Pay Debt to Estate of John C. Ragland, 1824 March 5, ANS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:37)
    A promissory note for $27.50 to the estate of John C. Ragland.
  - William Bernard to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1824 September 25, ALS, 1 p. with attached address leaf; docketed; Postmarked Fredericksburg, VA, September 30. (Box-folder 1:38)
    Expressing a desire to purchase property near Charlottesville in the Pantops area.
  - William J. Wickham to Th[omas] Jefferson Randolph, 1825 April 25, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. with address on verso; docketed; Postmarked Richmond, VA, April 25. (Box-folder 1:39)
    Declaring his intention to pay the court the proceeds from selling the Warren Estate, and asks him to attend to a motion by Scruggs about a debt due to him. Also asks about a debt owed to Mr. Nicholas, and other financial matters.
  - Thomas Jefferson Randolph's Account Book, 1826 - 1835, ANsS, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:40)
    Lists of Randolph's debts and assets.
  - Excerpts from The Richmond Enquirer, 1826 July, TNs, 4 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 1:41)
    Containing excerpts from "curious and authentic Memoir... in the handwriting of Mr. Jefferson," about his life and activities, and mentioning his career in politics, time as Visitor and Rector of the University, and his specific legislative services.
  - Reuben G. Clarkson to T[homas] J[efferson] Randolph, 1831 December 26, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:42)
    Concerning surveying land including [Creacy's] Land, and other properties.
  - Fragment of Duplicate of Promise of Payment on Loan, 1867 April 20, AL, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:43)
    Concerning advancing [Dr. T. A. Michie] money for his tobacco crop with calculations on verso.
  - Promissory Note from Nicholas Trist to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1827 January 15, ADS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:44)
    A promissory note from Nicholas P. Trist to Thomas Jefferson Randolph for one hundred sixty seven dollars.
  - Joseph Coolidge to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1829 April 3, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. with address on verso; with wax seal; docketed; Postmarked Boston, April 3. (Box-folder 1:45)
    Mentions her intentions to send a Profile, [The Medallion Portrait, 1805 of Thomas Jefferson by Gilbert Stuart] to Mr. Littell of Philadelphia, and that she has not received the Preface Randolph had sent her. She proposes that he send the Preface to the [Memoir, Correspondence, and Miscellanies, from the Papers of Thomas Jefferson]. Mr. Gray of the North American Review and who would like to take subscribers "for all this side of Pennsylvania" suggests a delay before attempting to acquire subscribers until the publication of [George] Washington's works. He would like the Profile returned briefly, if possible, to have a copy made for himself. In subsequent continuations, Coolidge relates further negotiations to find a person to take subscriptions for Randolph's Preface.
  - Joseph Coolidge to Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1830 May 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with attached address leaf; docketed; Postmarked Boston, May 17. (Box-folder 1:46)
    Concerning a misunderstanding concerning the employment of Mr. Gray to acquire subscribers. Assures Randolph that Mr. Gray will not interfere with any subscribers that Randolph has already acquired, and requests a list of places where Randolph has already taken subscriptions so that there will be no competition or overlap between them.
  - Margaret to Jane Randolph, 1832 September 24, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. with address on verso; Postmarked Baltimore, September 24. (Box-folder 1:47)
    Mentions relations and friends Hollins, John, and Jane M, Wilson, Lewis. She relates that "cousin Jane" is very ill, and inquires about the state of affairs near Jane Randolph's home.
  - Special Edition of The Globe Newspaper, 1840 August 12 (Box-folder 1:48)
    Original in Newspaper- Washington D.C.
  - Sidney Carr to Jane Hollins Nicholas Randolph, 1846 April 26, ALS, 3 pp. on 2 l. with address on verso; Postmarked Baltimore, April 27. (Box-folder 1:49)
    Claims that "his father's threat has had the desired effect upon Wilson," and expresses concern that there are barely enough children at her school to pay the teachers. Relates that Wilson is home from Yale, and Margaret Nicholas' daily visits to her ailing mother. Expects the arrival of Mrs. Thomas, and says she will decline paying her traveling expenses, but will be happy to have her visit.
  - Jane Hollins Nicholas Randolph to Ellen Wayles Randolph, 1846 October 3, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. with address on verso; Postmarked Charlottesville, October 4. (Box-folder 1:50)
    Concerning a land transaction, and says that Ellen's "father will go for the 50,000, but if he only got 25, that he could afford to divide his part of Shadwell between Frank & John." Relates family business, and discusses a large yield of apples from the "New Orchard."
  - Receipt for Purchase of Corn by Confederate States of America and Account of Purchase and Sale of Stocks, 1862, 2 items. (Box-folder 1:51)
    Receipt for the purchase of corn for the Confederate States of America, and a list of stocks bought and sold..
  - Meriwether Lewis to Mr. & Mrs. Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1862 July 3, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:52)
    Informing his parents that he is well and unhurt as are all of their officers during the Civil War.
  - Announcement of School Terms and Prices for the Edge Hill School, 1866 and 1895 to 1896, 2 items. (Box-folder 1:53)
  - Cary R. Ruffin toCaroline Ramsey Randolph, 1871 February 22, ALS, 1 p. with address on verso. (Box-folder 1:54)
    Concerning her studies and things she needs.
  - A Memorial of Col[onel] Thomas J[efferson] Randolph, 1875 October 22, Printed pamphlet, 11 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 1:55)
    Printed pamphlet that contains excerpts from the Charlottesville Chronicle of October 22nd, 1875. A retrospective of Randolph's life, including anecdotes about his childhood memories, his role in Virginia politics, his views on slavery, and his part in the Civil War. Provides a detailed account of Randolph's illnesses in later life, and his death. Contains an extended description of his deathbed scene, a visit from his pastor, Mr. Hanckel, and his final days. Also contains an excerpt of a letter from "An Old Student," reminiscing about his interactions with Randolph while he was at the University of Virginia.
  - John S. H. Fogg to [Sarah Nicholas] Randolph, 1886 January 17, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:56)
    Describing his interest in acquiring a letter of Mrs. [Martha] Jefferson and [Martha (Patsy) Jefferson] "who was the 'Lady of the White House' during the administration of Mr. Jefferson," his confinement for the past thirteen years, and his "hobby of collecting letters." A detailed description of his letter collections, his adulation of Mr. Jefferson's elegance and style, and "10 or 15 very elegant letters of Mr. Jefferson" on religion.
  - John Dunlop to Sarah [Nicholas Randolph], 1887 May 25, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box-folder 1:57)
    Thanks her for a copy of The Nation, in which she published The Kentucky Resolutions in a New Light, and concerning the superabundance of the "fame" of Mr. Jefferson and the Breckenridges. Mentions a recent plaster sculpture by [Edward V.] Valentine of John C. Breckenridge to be cast in bronze for Lexington. He recommends, in agreement with Randolph Harrison, that Valentine should "carry out the [General Robert E.] Lee monument." Provides an anecdote about an old confederate stonemason who would donate a days wages and would collect donations if Valentine were comissioned for the monument, "but if a foreigner gets it they would give nothing." He is currently reading and reccomends the Continuity of Christian Thought by [Alexander] Allen.
  - [Caroline Randolph] to Eliza Ruffin, 1888 October 19, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:58)
    Worried about the fate of a letter written to Eliza following the death of her aunt, Nanny [Randolph] which had not been received. A long description of Nanny's vomiting, talk with her husband Wilson [Cary Nicholas Randolph], discussion with Doctor Dabney, and her death.
  - Paul Leicester Ford to [Sarah Nicholas] Randolph, 1892 January 22, TLS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:59)